我，脇坂，已经击败了朝鲜南军。
I, Wakizaka, have defeated
Joseon's southern army,
虽以寡敌众, 仍取得了胜利。
achieving victory though far outnumbered.
我已协助大军北进，确保朝鲜首都汉阳掌控在我军手中。
I have aided our northern advance,
securing Joseon's capital Hanyang.
只剩下朝鲜水军仍在在南部海岸
Only Joseon's navy continues to resurface
不断滋扰。
on the southern coast.
我现在就出征去摧毁他们。
I now set out to destroy them.
大名阁下，
Lord Chancellor,
我们将按计划准备好迎接您的到来。
we will be ready for your arrival
as planned.
日本文禄元年，来自淡路的脇坂。
(译者注：即明朝万历二十年)
Bunroku year one, Wakizaka of Awaji.
[1592年6月，庆尚道釜山浦倭军基地]
WAE ENEMY (FOREIGN ISLANDS) BASE,
BUSANPO, GYEONGSANG-DO, JUNE 1592
谢谢你。
Thank you.
[脇坂安治]
WAKIZAKA YASUHARU
沐海潛(一种海怪)？
Bokkaisen (sea monster)?
大人。
Dono. (lord)
我们的敌人李舜臣建造了一艘新船。
Our foe Yi Sun-shin built a new ship.
它看起来来势汹汹。
It looked menacing,
就像一个沐海潛。
just like a Bokkaisen,
神话中的海怪。
the mythical sea monster.
我们的枪是没有用的。
Our guns were useless.
它有一个喷火的龙头。
It had a dragon head spouting fire.
我们感到极度恐惧。
We were struck by sheer terror.
你是说沐海潛呀。
Bokkaisen, you say.
恐惧是会传染的啊。
Fear is a contagion.
这艘船被撞了吗？
Was the ship rammed?
已在泗川海岸被毁。
Wrecked off the Sacheon coast.
我们把它拖到了这里。
We hauled it here.
[一个月前，朝鲜东南部庆尚道泗川市]
A MONTH AGO, SACHEON
GYEONGSANG-DO, SOUTHEAST JOSEON
[李恩良队长]
向后划！
CHIEF LEE EON-RYANG
Row backward!
我们必须挣脱束缚!
We must break loose!
向后划!
Row backward!
[罗大用队长]
CHIEF NAH DAE-YONG
准备立刻发射龙头和所有前炮！
Prepare to fire the dragon head
and all front cannons at once!
赶紧上膛!
Load them now!
开火！
Fire!
是沐海潛!
It's the Bokkaisen!
开火！
Fire!
[釜山要塞]
BUSAN FORTRESS
1592年4月13日,
ON APRIL 13, 1592,
釜山要塞遭到倭国入侵者的袭击。
BUSAN FORTRESS WAS ATTACKED
BY WAE INVADERS.
[汉阳](现为首尔)
HANYANG
倭国军队攻克了釜山要塞。
WAE FORCES OVERTOOK BUSAN FORTRESS,
在20天内就占领了朝鲜首都汉阳。
OCCUPYING JOSEON'S CAPITAL HANYANG
IN 20 DAYS.
[平壤]
PYEONGYANG
当倭国侵略者向北席卷而来时，朝鲜国王宣宗向北逃到平壤。
KING SEONJO FLED NORTH TO PYEONGYANG
AS THE WAE INVADERS SWEPT NORTHWARD.
[光教山]
GWANGGYOSAN
来自全罗道、庆尚道和忠清道的50,000名士兵
50,000 SOLDIERS FROM THE PROVINCES JEOLLA,
GYEONGSANG, AND CHUNGCHEONG
聚集在光教山以夺回首都汉阳。
GATHERED AT GWANGGYOSAN MOUNTAIN
TO RECAPTURE THE CAPITAL HANYANG.
[龙仁光教山]
GWANGGYOSAN MOUNTAIN, YONGIN
但在1592年6月5日，
BUT ON JUNE 5, 1592,
脇坂带着2,000人倭军伏击并摧毁了朝鲜军队。
WAKIZAKA AMBUSHED WITH 2,000 MEN,
DESTROYING JOSEON'S ARMY.
朝鲜似乎正处于被毁灭的边缘。
JOSEON APPEARED TO BE
ON THE BRINK OF RUIN.
然而于此同时，在庆尚道固城郡的南海岸,
MEANWHILE, ON THE SOUTHERN COAST
OF GOSEONG, GYEONGSANG-DO,
却有20艘入侵的倭国战舰在唐项浦被歼灭,
20 WAE SHIPS WERE DESTROYED AT DANGHANGPO
那是因为全罗左道水军节度使李舜臣还在海上孤军奋战.
AS THE LEFT JEOLLA NAVY ADMIRAL
YI SUN-SHIN BATTLED ALONE AT SEA.
他在第一次海战中横跨玉浦、合浦和赤珍浦,
IN HIS FIRST NAVAL CAMPAIGN
ACROSS OKPO, HAPPO, AND JEOKJINPO,
摧毁了42艘倭国战舰。
HE DESTROYED 42 WAE SHIPS.
在他的第二次战役中，再次鏖战于泗川、唐浦、唐项浦，
BATTLING IN HIS SECOND CAMPAIGN
ACROSS SACHEON, DANGPO, DANGHANPO,
之前的枪伤让他备受煎熬。
HE SUFFERED AN EARLY GUNSHOT WOUND.
闲山：龙的出现
HANSAN: RISING DRAGON
[距离第三次海战还有五天]
FIVE DAYS TILL THE THIRD NAVAL CAMPAIGN
龟甲舰...
The turtle ship...
将军。宋军士报告。
Admiral. Sergeant Song reporting.
元将军已经到了。
Admiral Won has arrived.
[宋辉锐军士]
我去准备。叫仆人进来。
SERGEANT SONG HUI-RIP
I'll get ready. Send in the servant.
遵命，大人。
Yes, sir.
[丽水, 全罗左道水军总部]
LEFT JEOLLA NAVY HEADQUARTERS, YEOSU
什么？先发制人的攻击？
What? A preemptive strike?
[庆尚道水军右使元均]
你疯了吗？
RIGHT GYEONGSANG NAVY, ADMIRAL WON GYUN
Have you gone mad?
[指挥官郑运]
我们必须尽快夺回釜山。
COMMANDER JUNG UN
We must hasten to recapture Busan.
现在是我们让倭国入侵者措手不及的时候了。
Now is our time to catch
the Wae invaders off guard.
我们必须先下手为强。
We must strike first.
除非我们攻击他们的主基地，否则打几个小胜仗是没有用的。
Minor victories are useless
unless we attack their main base.
嗯，嗯...
Well, well...
你仍然醉心于那些小的胜利。
You're still drunk
on those minor victories.
釜山的敌军将领在龙仁发起了光教山战役。
The enemy general in Busan led
the Battle of Gwanggyosan in Yongin.
你不记得在光教山与敌军作战的
Do you not recall
Chief Commander Lee Gwang,
李洸总指挥了吗？
who attacked the enemy
at Gwanggyosan Mountain?
他的部队被歼灭了!
His men were annihilated!
他因战败而受到指责，被视为叛徒。
He is blamed for the defeat,
deemed a traitor.
这是战局所迫啊。
There is a tide of war.
我们必须防守，而非进攻!
We must defend, not attack!
告诉我。你同意他的观点吗？
Tell me. Do you agree with him?
还是你的下属们都疯了？
Or have your underlings gone mad?
- 注意你的言辞！- 下属？
- Watch your words!
- Underlings?
元将军。
Admiral Won,
[全罗右道水军节度使李亿祺]
你有更好的主意吗？
RIGHT JEOLLA NAVY, ADMIRAL LEE EOK-GI
do you have a better idea?
防守!坚壁清野!
Defense! Ironclad defense!
凭借海上的坚固屏障,
With an ironclad barrier on the sea,
我们将保卫全罗左道水军总部。
we'll defend the
Left Jeolla Navy Headquarters.
我会烧毁庆尚右道临时水军总部,
I'll burn down the provisional
Right Gyeongsang Navy Headquarters,
并在这里加入你的水军。
joining you here instead.
由我们的联合舰队共同御敌的话,
With our joint fleet
fending off the enemy,
我们总部难道不会是一个坚不可摧的堡垒吗？
won't our headquarters here be
a steely fortress?
[庆尚北道水军指挥李云龙]
RIGHT GYEONGSANG NAVY
COMMANDER LEE UN-RYONG
像你这样的长者不用为我送行。
An elder such as yourself
need not see me out.
[全罗左道水军指挥鱼泳潭]
因为当年你是我教出来的新兵蛋子,
LEFT JEOLLA NAVY, COMMANDER EO YOUNG-DAM
Since you're a former cadet
而现在已经是一个身经百战的指挥官了,
now busy as a commander,
难得让你陪陪老师我
this is an old teacher's chance
的机会啊。
to enjoy rare company.
你的精神状态一如既往地好。
You're in good spirits as always.
而且身体看上去也很棒。
And in good health, it seems.
绝非如此。
By no means.
我一直在一个可怕的上司手下被折磨。
I'm suffering under a dreadful superior.
但你对可怕的上司并不陌生。
But you're no stranger
to dreadful superiors.
唉，我们的痛苦是一样的。
Alas, we suffer alike.
晚安，大人。
Good night, sir.
[庆尚道釜山浦倭军基地]
WAE (FOREIGN ISLANDS) ENEMY BASE,
BUSANPO, GYEONSANG-DO
大名已经对你
The lord chancellor has
寄予厚望。
high hopes for you.
欢迎您的到来,
You are welcome here,
军师大人。
advisor.
我看到你的人好像很忙碌。
I saw your men looking busy.
是不是太着急了？
Isn't it too soon for haste?
[黑田康兵卫(又名黑田孝高), 大名的军师]
KURODA KANBEI
LORD CHANCELLOR'S ADVISOR
在这里。
Here.
大名大人已经给出了他的答复。
The lord chancellor sends his reply.
在光教山的龙仁之战中。
In the Battle of Yongin
at Gwanggyosan Mountain,
你知道我是如何用两千人消灭五万人的吗？
do you know how I destroyed 50,000 men
with only 2,000?
为什么这么问？
Why,
你用一个先发制人的伏击打的他们措手不及。
you caught them unawares
with a preemptive ambush.
[丽水，李舜臣总部]
YEOSU
Yi Sun-shin's headquarters here
必须马上打垮。
must be struck down immediately.
然后...
And then...
然后呢？
Then?
我们必须在平壤北面增援小西的师团。
We must reinforce Konishi's division
up north in Pyeongyang.
一旦我们这样做,
Once we do,
才能最终完成对朝鲜的征服。
our conquest of Joseon shall be complete.
令人印象深刻。
Impressive.
不愧是大名大人的杰出武士。
Worthy of the lord chancellor's
preeminent warrior.
平壤北面的小西将会
Konishi up north in Pyeongyang
对你感恩戴德，鞠躬致谢。
will be beholden to you,
bowing in gratitude.
我认为你会像其他将军一样加快行动
I thought you might hasten
like the other generals
直指明朝。
straight to Ming China.
我很担心。
I was concerned.
无疑，你也渴望
No doubt, you also crave
征服中国。
the conquest of Ming China.
然而。
However,
我建议不要进行单独的行动。
I advise against a solo campaign.
就目前的情况来看，没有必要去冒这个险。
As things now stand,
there is no need for risk.
最好是全力以赴地领导一场联合战役。
Better to lead a joint campaign
at full force.
我明白。
I understand.
因此,
Hence,
我有一个请求。
I have a request.
关于加藤的，我猜？
About Kato, I presume?
[全罗左道水军总部龟甲船船坞]
TURTLE SHIP DOCKYARD
LEFT JEOLLA NAVY HEADQUARTERS
你要去掉龙头？
You're removing the dragon head?
自从泗川之战后，我一直在思考。
Since the Battle of Sacheon,
I've been thinking.
我彻夜难眠，无法动摇你
I stayed up nights
unable to shake the belief
需要龟船的信念
that you need the turtle ship.
它不会再在撞击时被卡住吗？
Will it no longer get lodged upon ramming?
这是解决这个问题的唯一途径。
It's the only way to solve that problem.
它的速度也会提高吗？
Will it also improve its speed?
是的，大人。
Indeed, sir.
一艘无头龟船...
A headless turtle ship...
你听说了吗？
Have you heard?
最新抵达釜山的倭国入侵者...
The latest Wae invaders to arrive
in Busan...
我听说他们是相当可怕的。
I hear they're quite formidable.
李水使的命令执行得怎么样了？
How is Admiral Yi's order coming along?
嗯...
Well...
[炮长李奉洙]
GUNNERY MASTER
LEE BONG-SU
...我们正在收集
...we're gathering
所有能从老百姓那里拿到的火药原料。
all the gunpower ingredients we can,
sourcing it from the people.
但龟船的胃口太好了。
But the turtle ships guzzle so much.
他们是嗑火药的怪兽。
Gunpowder-guzzling monsters, they are.
龟甲舰可以加入水使的舰队,
The turtle ships can join
the admiral's fleet
如果你们抓紧一点的话。
only if you make haste.
除了冲撞, 负责撞击的船只必须做的更多。
The ramming ships must do more than ram.
对。
Right.
顺便说一下。
By the way,
这是给你的。
this is for you.
这是什么？
What's this?
我亲手抓住了这只小动物。
I caught the critter myself.
如果你有一天感到孤独或气馁，它可以让你振作起来。
If you ever get lonely or discouraged,
it can cheer you up.
- 嘲笑我，是吗？- 别紧张。
- Mocking me, are you?
- Take it easy.
如果你愿意的话，可以煮一碗龟汤补补身子。
Cook a turtle soup for your health
if you'd like.
在你行尸走肉之前。
Before you become a shell of a man.
无耻。
That impudence.
防守!坚守!
Defense! Ironclad defense!
我们必须防守，而不是攻击!
We must defend, not attack!
我有一封总司令李洸寄自全州要塞的信。
I have a letter from Jeonju Fortress
sent by Chief Commander Lee Gwang.
回忆在光教山的败绩
He was pained
对他来说非常痛苦。
to recall his defeat
at Gwanggyosan Mountain.
倭军的脇坂没有留下
The enemy Wakizaka
守卫水原要塞。
did not stay behind
to guard Suwon Fortress.
相反，他向永仁的光教山进发，
Instead, he advanced
to Yongin's Gwanggyosan Mountain,
不断地骚扰和迷惑我们的部队。
tiring and luring our troops.
当我们的人降低警惕并在
When our men lowered their guard,
一片空地上安营扎寨之时，
setting up camp in an open field,
脇坂在黎明时分伏击并歼灭了我们的部队。
Wakizaka ambushed at dawn,
annihilating our army.
他用进攻的战略守住了
His stronghold was defended
他的要塞。
without a defensive strategy.
李水使。
Admiral Yi.
陛下发来消息。
His Majesty sends word.
发生了什么事？
What has happened?
我们收到来自平壤的消息。
We received word from Pyeongyang.
陛下已经动身前往西北边境的义州。
HIS MAJESTY HAS DEPARTED TO UIJU
BY THE NORTHWEST BORDER.
他怎么能放弃平壤呢？
How could he forsake Pyeongyang Fortress?
有比平壤更重要的事。
There is more at stake than Pyeongyang.
我们必须要知道为什么陛下要去
We must ask why His Majesty left for Uiju
西北边境的义州？
by the northwest border.
总指挥倾向于去东北的咸镜道，
The Chief Commander preferred
the northeast province Hamgyeong-do
那里可以作为一个防御基地。
as a defensible base,
但陛下却选择了西北边境的义州。
but His Majesty chose Uiju
by the northwest border instead.
陛下是否会
Will His Majesty
向西寻求明朝的庇护（内附中国）？
seek refuge westward in Ming China?
这是不可能的。
That cannot be.
这会摧毁所有人的士气
It will destroy the people's morale
并威胁到我们家园的命运。
and threaten the fate of our land.
根据我们与朝鲜囚犯的训练，
Based on our training
with Joseon prisoners,
朝鲜水军的大炮射程达到了1000码。
Joseon's navy cannons reach a firing range
of 1,000 yards.
在500码内具有破坏性。
They are destructive within 500 yards.
[渡辺七右衛門] 在100码内能做到准确瞄准。
WATANABE SHICHIEMON
They aim accurately within 100 yards.
一百码。
One hundred yards.
他们的板屋船（一种朝鲜战舰）
Their panokseon (Joseon warships)
有一种奇怪炮弹装弹方法。
have a strange way of reloading cannons.
怎么说呢？
How so?
将战舰调转至另一边开火
Instead of reloading,
they rotate their ships,
而不是重新装弹。
firing from the other side.
非常有趣啊。
Interesting.
然而，
However,
即使他们的板屋战舰以这种方式进行更快的射击，
even if their panokseon ships refire
faster that way,
但我们可以在200码外用速度优势
we can press with speed
from 200 yards away,
超过他们的战舰来压制他们。
overtaking their ships.
从200码开始，
From 200 yards,
超过他们。
overtaking them.
大人。
Dono.
我们必须再次进行伏击。
We must ambush again.
[真锅左马充]
立即部署舰队。
MANABE SAMANOSUKE
Deploy the fleet at once.
如果他们阻止我们。
If they block us,
我们会碾碎那个麻烦的东西。
we will crush that troublesome thing.
你是说海怪沐海潛。
You mean the sea monster Bokkaisen,
或者说他们的龟甲舰（盲船）？
or rather their mekurabune (blind ship)?
龟甲舰。
Mekurabune.
盲船。
Blind ship.
我喜欢这个名字，比沐海潛好听。
I like that name better than Bokkaisen.
龟甲舰只打了一场仗。
The mekurabune fought only one battle.
但为什么只打了一场呢？
But why?
为什么他们不会将被谣传为
Why won't they battle with a ship
怪兽的战舰投入战斗？
rumored to be a monstrous Bokkaisen?
佐平。
Sahei.
你有两天时间。
You have two days.
去侦察一下全罗左道的水军。
Go scout the Left Jeolla Navy.
了解龟甲舰的情况。
Find out about the mekurabune.
还有，
Also,
打听一下李舜臣。
about Yi Sun-shin.
渡边。
Watanabe.
小早川领导的第六师团
About Kobayakawa
leading the sixth division
在全罗道附近的锦山。
in Geumsan near Jeolla-do.
我必须给他带个话。
I must send word to him.
将军。
Admiral.
李水使。
Admiral Yi.
我们这里的总部可能是国王陛下最后的避难所。
Our headquarters here might be
His Majesty's last refuge.
与其匆忙上阵，
Instead of rushing to battle,
也许我们应该像元水使建议的那样守住这个地方。
perhaps we should guard this place
as Admiral Won suggested.
你还是会进攻
Will you still attack
在釜山要塞的倭军基地吗？
the Wae invaders' base at Busan Fortress?
在你眼里是这样的吗？
Does it look so in your eyes?
难道不是这样吗？
Is it not so?
也许是这样。
Perhaps it is.
但正如元水使所言，
But as Admiral Won has said,
我们处于防守状态。
we're on the defensive.
对釜山的行动需要谨慎。
An attack on Busan requires caution.
如果你既不防守也不进攻。
If you will neither defend nor attack,
你的作战计划是什么？
what is your battle plan?
也许
Perhaps
我们的下一场战斗将决定
our next battle will determine
这场战争的走向。。
the fate of this war.
[兴国寺避难所] 饭团!
HEUNGGUKSA TEMPLE REFUGE
Rice balls!
大米!
Rice!
请慢用。
Please have some food.
那个人我怎么在釜山要塞也看到过。
I saw that man at Busan Fortress.
有趣。
Interesting.
- 要小心。- 好的。
- Be careful.
- All right.
我已收到你的信。
I have received your letter.
我感谢你的提议。
I appreciate the offer,
但作为第六师团的指挥官，
but as commander of the sixth division,
我，小早川，将按计划进攻全州要塞。
I, Kobayakawa, will attack Jeonju Fortress
as planned.
锦山要塞刚刚摆脱了朝鲜勤王军。
Now that Geumsan Fortress is cleared
of the Joseon people's militia,
我很快就能向全罗道的全州要塞进军。
I can soon advance on Jeonju Fortress
in Jeolla-do.
请写下我的答复。
Transcribe my reply.
我请求你攻打李舜臣的全罗左道水军总部,
Instead of attacking Jeonju Fortress
with the sixth division,
而不是让第六师攻打全州要塞。
I ask you to strike Yi Sun-shin's
Left Jeolla Navy Headquarters.
如果你这样做，你将会获得我在全罗道征服的一切。
Do so, and I will grant you
all my conquests in Jeolla-do.
战争的结果取决于全罗左道水军，而不是全州要塞。
The war's outcome depends on
the Left Jeolla Navy, not Jeonju Fortress.
现在，和我一起参加这次进击吧，
Now, join me in this attack,
这会让大名大人满意的。
which will please the lord chancellor.
大人。
Dono.
你会把整个全罗道都交给小早川吗？
Will you grant Kobayakawa
all of Jeolla-do?
李舜臣只是一个障碍，我们可以在没有他的帮助下战胜他。
Yi is a mere hindrance we can defeat
without his help.
仅仅是一个阻碍？
A mere hindrance?
你将如何打败李舜臣？
How will you defeat Yi?
通过先发制人的打击，让他措手不及。
By catching him off guard
with a preemptive strike!
就像我们在光教山所做的那样!
As we did at Gwanggyosan!
让我们保持领先一步。
Let's stay one step ahead.
我们也会在陆地上打败他。
We'll defeat him also on land.
这是一个全面胜利的计划，我有这个计划，而李舜臣却没有。
It's a plan for total victory,
which I have while Yi doesn't.
- 我们已经准备好了......--朝鲜很快就会沦陷。
- But we're ready--
- Joseon will fall soon.
战争将转移到大明的中国。
The war will shift to Ming China.
从征服大明开始。
By reaching Ming first,
我们将征服更多。
we will conquer much more.
相比之下，全罗道就显得有些逊色了。
Jeolla-do pales in comparison.
你不明白吗？
Do you not understand?
但是
But
加藤的舰队能及时到达吗？
will Kato's fleet arrive in time?
康兵卫是一个言出必行的人。
Kanbei is a man of his word.
他会做到的。
He will make it happen.
你在泗川的手下为什么要加入靠近全罗锦山的师团？
Why did your men at Sacheon join
the division at Geumsan near Jeolla?
他们是否会从锦山进攻全州要塞？
Will they deploy from Geumsan
to attack Jeonju Fortress?
他们什么时候进攻？
When will they strike?
我什么都不知道。
I know nothing.
什么都不知道。
Nothing at all.
不知道。
Nothing.
你们这些傻瓜!
You fools!
全州要塞问题不大。
Jeonju Fortress matters little.
我们的部队正在釜山
Our Wae army is gathering
聚集大批的士兵。
in great numbers in Busan.
朝鲜将会在我们前往中国和印度
Joseon will be annihilated
的途中被剿灭。
on our way to Ming China and India.
你们应该乞求你们的性命!
You should beg for your lives!
你是谁？
Who are you?
- 将军!- 将军！
- Admiral!
为什么，你！？
Why, you!
你怎么敢！？
How dare you!
大人!
Dono!
他们对他做了什么？
What have they done to him?
你还好吗？
Are you alright?
大人!
Dono!
因为有你， 我们才在这里甘愿忍受折磨。
You're the reason we endure.
你是我们大家的英雄!
You're a hero to us all!
不要杀他。
Do not take his life.
我感觉他有话要说。
I sense he has a veiled purpose.
这场战争...
This war...
它是关于什么的？
What is it about?
我恳请你告诉我。
I beseech you to tell me.
这场战争是什么？
What is this war?
一场正义与不义的战斗。
A battle of the righteous
against the unrighteous.
不是国与国之争？
Not a battle of nations?
不是。
No.
我在泗川向你开过枪。
I shot you at Sacheon.
我亲眼所见
I saw with my own eyes
你如何站出来拯救你的士兵。
how you stepped forth
to save your soldier.
但我的指挥官
But my commander
用我们的人做盾牌
used us men as shields
来拯救他自己。
to save himself.
请。让我为你效忠吧。
Please. Let me serve you.
[咸镜道鹿屯岛(东北边境)]
NOKDUNDO ISLAND,
HAMGYEONG-DO (NORTHEAST BORDER)
我为什么会梦到这个？
Why did I dream of this?
他守住了堡垒
His stronghold was defended
却没有用防守的战略。
without a defensive strategy.
没有防守的防守
Defended
却守住了。
without a defensive strategy.
[第三次海战前三天]
THREE DAYS TILL THE THIRD NAVAL CAMPAIGN
这个阵型是防御性的吗？还是进攻性的？
Is this formation defensive? Or offensive?
当然是防御性的。就像海面上的屏障。
Surely defensive.
Like a barrier on the sea.
海上的屏障？
A barrier on the sea?
在那边。
Over there,
我们正在模拟倭国入侵者的攻击。
we're simulating the Wae invaders' attack.
这很像实战啊。
It's quite realistic.
鹤翼队形。
Crane wing formation.
是的，将军。
Yes, Admiral.
鹤翼队形!
Crane wing formation!
我们必须向左翼移动。
We must move to the left wing.
遵命，大人。
Yes, sir.
去右翼的中心。
To the right wing's center.
快点！
On the double.
遵命，大人。
Yes, sir.
我们要相撞了!
We're colliding!
注意你的位置!
Watch your position!
再往左移动一点!
Go farther left!
我们应该在左翼的中心位置!
We're due at the left wing's center!
右翼看起来不稳定。
The right wing looks unsteady.
不要紧。让我们迎头痛击吧。
Never mind. We'll go head-on.
- 把梯子抬起来。- 抬起来！
- Raise the ladders.
- Raise them!
转动船只。
Rotate the ship.
转!
Rotate!
停止左舷船桨！
Port oars, stop!
转!
Rotate!
右舷船桨，划快点！
Starboard oars, row faster!
回到队列!
Back to formation!
- 转头。- 转头!
- Rotate.
- Rotate!
调头!
Rotate!
港口船桨，停止！转动！
Port oars, stop! Rotate!
大人，我们不能在这么短的距离内转动船只。
Sir, we can't rotate
within such short distance.
元将军那些缺乏训练的船只不要参战了吧。
Not with Admiral Won's ships
that lack training.
让他留在队列中吧。
Keep him in the formation.
把这个交给李亿祺将军。
And deliver this to Admiral Lee Eok-gi.
是的，大人。
Yes, sir.
转动船身!
Rotate the ship!
报告，大人。
Reporting, sir.
自泗川之战后。
Since the Battle of Sacheon,
在训练中从未见过龟甲舰。
the mekurabune was never seen in training.
龟甲舰一定有问题。
There must be a problem
with the mekurabune.
我们必须找出它是什么。
We must find out what it is.
我们要潜入他们的总部。
We'll enter their headquarters.
我们走吧。
Let's move.
- 着火啦！- 你想要什么？
- Fire!
- What do you want?
- 你是谁？- 我们是站在你这边的。
- Who are you?
- We're on your side.
囚犯的牢房着火了!
The prisoners' cells are on fire!
囚犯们正在逃跑！追击他们！
The prisoners are escaping! After them!
难怪你这个和尚看起来很凶残。
No wonder you looked murderous for a monk.
抓住他们！抓住犯人！
Catch them! Catch the prisoners!
龟甲舰着火了!
The turtle ship is in flames!
扑灭火！现在！
Put out the fire! Now!
跟着我。
Follow me.
你们竟然管成这个样子？
You call yourselves officers in charge?
守护龟甲舰是你们的职责!
It's your duty to guard the turtle ship!
在任何时候都不例外!
At all times with no exception!
这是玩忽职守!
This is a failure in duty!
将军。恐怕那个探子头目逃跑了。
Admiral. I'm afraid the head spy escaped.
我们让你失望了，大人。
We've failed you, sir.
快走，快点！
Move! Hurry up!
快点!
Hurry up!
将军。
Admiral.
有几名囚犯失踪。
A few prisoners are missing.
快点!
Hurry up!
- 将军。- 龟甲舰有无损坏？
- Admiral.
- Any damages to the turtle ship?
[李吉男队长] 有些烧伤,但并不严重。
CHIEF LEE GI-NAM
Some scorches. Nothing serious.
探子头目偷了龟甲舰的建造计划。
The head spy stole
the turtle ship's construction plans.
罗队长在哪里？
Where is Chief Nah?
两天前就在顺天船坞了。
At the Suncheon dockyard
since two days ago.
让我们去那里吧。
Let us go there.
[靠近丽水的顺天秘密船坞]
SECRET DOCKYARD, SUNCHEON, NEAR YEOSU
这艘龟甲舰必须更厉害!
This turtle ship has to be better!
封住那个接头!
Seal that joint!
将军!将军。
Admiral! Admiral.
我听说了间谍的事。
I heard about the spies.
我很欣慰龟甲舰没有被损坏。
I'm relieved
that the turtle ships weren't damaged.
我被告知你正在重新安装龙头。
I am told
you're reattaching the dragon head.
是的，大人。
Yes, sir.
我们必须尽快发起战斗。
We must wage battle soon.
这艘龟甲舰会不会准备好？
Will this turtle ship be ready?
我们正在夜以继日地工作。
We're working night and day.
我们还需要几天时间。
We need a few more days.
间谍们带着你的建造计划
The spies escaped
逃跑了。
with your construction plans.
脇坂会了解到龟甲舰的弱点。
Wakizaka will learn
about the turtle ship's weaknesses.
将军。
Admiral.
这艘新的龟甲舰是不同的。
This new turtle ship is different.
我将在没有龟甲舰的情况下打这场仗。
I will fight this battle
without turtle ships.
我现在必须离开。
I must leave now.
将军。
Admiral.
侧面看起来很弱。
The sides look weak.
这有利于发射大炮，但一旦开战也容易暴露。
Good for firing cannons
but exposed to attack.
还有，
Also,
船的头部和上盖一定非常重。
the head and cover must be heavy.
我想知道它是否能以任何速度航行。
I wonder if it can sail with any speed.
俊沙，是吗？
Junsa, was it?
因此，你和这艘船战斗过。
So you fought against the ship.
是的，在泗川战役中。
Yes, at the Battle of Sacheon.
的确，它的行动似乎相当迟缓。
Indeed, its movement seemed quite slow.
继续。
Go on.
在泗川。
At Sacheon,
我们中了李舜臣的圈套。
we fell for Yi's luring tactic.
引诱战术？
Luring tactic?
是的，大人。
Yes, sir.
然而。
However,
正如你所指出的,
as you pointed out,
我们可以轻易地摧毁这艘船,
we could've easily destroyed the ship
如果我们有准备的话。
had we been prepared.
有一次，它撞上了我们的军舰。
Once it rammed into our warship,
龙头被卡住，无法移动。
the dragon head was lodged,
unable to move.
龙头被卡住了？
The dragon head was lodged?
是的，大人。
Yes, sir.
所以，这就是缺陷。
So, that was the flaw.
一次有问题的撞击。
A flawed ram.
然而。
And yet,
它被称为 "沐海潛"，在我们的人中引发了恐惧。
it was called the Bokkaisen,
striking terror in our men.
你是在暗示这是一个虚假的传言吗？
Are you implying it was a false rumor?
渡边。
Watanabe.
你怎么看？
What do you think?
因为它没有参加过训练。
Since it was absent from training,
它可能不会被投入实战。
it probably won't be deployed.
然而，我很关心佐平提供的有关朝鲜水军
However, I'm concerned
鹤翼阵型的报告。
by Sahei's report
regarding their crane wing formation.
似乎是一种攻击阵型。
It appears to be an offensive.
我怀疑他们会通过包围釜山浦来发动攻击。
I suspect they will surround Busanpo
to mount an attack.
不是的，大人。
No, sir.
李舜臣在利用囚犯
Yi was using prisoners
来准备防守战术。
to prepare defensive tactics.
此外，如果没有龟甲舰，
Besides, without the mekurabune,
他不会冒险进行进攻的。
he cannot risk an attack.
大人。这些都是毫无根据的说法。
Dono. These are baseless claims.
够了。
Enough.
俊沙。
Junsa.
靠近点。
Come closer.
再近一点。
Closer.
证明你的说法是正确的。
Justify your claim.
甚至他们的国王也逃到
Even their king has fled
了西北边界。
to the northwest border.
因此，李舜臣会寻求退路。
Hence, Yi will be looking to retreat.
他不敢贸然进攻。
He wouldn't dare advance in attack.
我必须说，
I must say,
这是一个很好的推理。
it's decent reasoning.
大人。加藤的舰队已经到达了。
Dono. Kato's fleet has arrived.
到的太是时候了。
Arriving at the perfect time.
[加藤嘉明]
KATO YOSHIAKI
[九鬼嘉隆]
KUKI YOSHITAKA
战神八幡
The war god Hachiman
再次照耀着我。
shines on me again.
将军!
Admiral!
没有龟甲舰，你能赢得战斗吗？
Can you win your battle
without the turtle ship?
没有龟甲舰，你真的能赢吗？
Can you truly win without the turtle ship?
你的伤口还没有痊愈。但你已经开始射箭了。
Your wound has yet to heal.
Yet you're shooting arrows already.
将军。
Admiral.
通过训练我深信
I'm convinced by our training
我们需要龟甲舰。
that we need the turtle ships.
你不同意吗？
Do you not agree?
将军。
Admiral.
大人。
Sir,
林俊英亲自带来了他的报告。
Lim Jun-young brought his report
in person.
他亲自来了？
In person?
截至目前，脇坂的舰队
Until now, Wakizaka's fleet
有30艘大型船只，70艘中型船只，
had 30 large ships, 70 medium ships,
合计一百艘。
One hundred ships total.
从南部对马岛出发的加藤嘉明的舰队（大船和小船各20艘）
Kato Yoshiaki's fleet
from the southern island Daemado
也已经加入了脇坂的舰队。
has now joined him
with 20 large ships and 20 small ships.
这样，总共有140艘。
That makes 140 ships total.
脇坂的等待已经结束。他会很快进行部署。
Wakizaka's wait is over.
He will deploy soon.
时机已到。
The time has arrived.
但是，大人。
But sir,
加藤的船非常特别。
Kato's ships are unique.
特别？
Unique?
几艘大船的船体较厚，
Several large ships have thicker hulls
还有我们以前没有见过的吊装式大炮。
and suspended cannons
we haven't seen before.
至于他们的旗舰，
As for their flagship,
它装备有大炮并覆盖有铁板。
it's armed with cannons
and covered in iron plates.
一艘覆盖着铁板的旗舰？
A flagship covered in iron plates?
果然不出所料。
It is as expected.
他们准备对付我们的大炮和撞角。
They prepared
against our cannons and rams.
这支敌军舰队...
This enemy fleet...
[权俊指挥]......将会发起进攻以保障通往
COMMANDER GWON JUN
...will attack to secure a supply route
西海岸的补给线。
to the western coast.
敌人的地面部队聚集在...
The enemy's ground troops are gathered...
[申镐指挥]......全州要塞附近的锦山。
COMMANDER SHIN HO
...at Geumsan near Jeonju Fortress.
他们将在海陆进行两线作战。
They will fight on two fronts at sea
and on land.
他们将同时攻击全州要塞和全罗左道水军。
They will attack both Jeonju Fortress
and the Left Jeolla Navy.
如果我们的水军如敌人所愿倒下了，
If our navy falls as the enemy wishes,
朝鲜在义州的政权也将垮台。
Joseon's regime in Uiju will also fall.
我们肯定会面临进攻，但全州受到的威胁更大。
We will surely face attack,
but Jeonju is under greater threat.
龙仁之战
The Battle of Yongin has left
把总指挥李洸打残了。
Chief Commander Lee Gwang
crippled by defeat.
无论如何，我们必须提醒全州要塞。
In any case,
we must alert Jeonju Fortress.
我们是不是应该分兵增援全州要塞？
Shouldn't we split our forces
to reinforce the army at Jeonju Fortress?
你疯了吗？我们不能让水师分兵。
Have you gone mad?
We cannot split the navy.
绝不能!
Out of the question!
忍住你的怒火。我只是说我必须这样做。
Hold your anger. I merely speak as I must.
够了。
Enough.
李水使。
Admiral Yi.
你准备如何作战？
How will you proceed?
现在是进行关键战斗的时候了。
The time has come for a critical battle.
因此...
Hence...
明天午夜，我们出征。
tomorrow at midnight,
we shall set out to war.
为战斗做好准备。
Prepare for deployment.
不进行防守？
Instead of defending?
而是装填炮弹和火药!
Load the shells and gunpowder!
小心点!
Careful!
按照命令，
As ordered,
[炮长李奉洙] 我们囤了所有能囤的火药。
GUNNERY MASTER LEE BONG-SU
we stockpiled all the gunpowder we could.
做得好。
Well done.
为什么你需要的量比平时多？
Why do you need more than usual?
双倍装弹量的大炮
For double-loading cannons
可以同时装填炮弹和霰弹。
with both shells and shrapnel shells.
这只能在短距离内造成伤害。
That will cause damage
only within short range.
- 到时敌舰会接近我们的......--了解了。
- The enemy ships will close in--
- Noted.
罗队长在路上了吗？
Is Chief Nah on his way?
让我们一起享受这杯酒。
Let's enjoy this drink together.
顺便说一下。
By the way,
这个李水使是个什么样的人？
what kind of man is this Admiral Yi?
一个令人惊讶的强大敌人。
A surprisingly strong foe.
这就是为什么我们必须一起面对他。
That is why we must face him together.
我听说朝鲜的将领一直很孱弱，
Joseon's commanders have been weak,
I heard.
但李舜臣一定是个例外。
Yi must be the exception.
现在，两位战神都在这里加入我们了，
Now that two war heroes have
joined us here,
李舜臣不会有机会的。
Yi will not stand a chance.
这场沉闷的战争将比预期结束地更快。
This dull war will end sooner
than expected.
大人。
Dono.
我们收到了来自小早川第六师团的消息。
We received word
from Kobayakawa's sixth division.
所有人都出去。
Everyone out.
如果你想死的话，就不要犹豫了。
Dither at your peril if you wish to die!
快点!
Hurry up!
小早川同意对从陆路对全罗左道水军总部进行攻击。
Kobayakawa agreed to the inland attack
against the Left Jeolla Navy Headquarters.
在这种情况下，
In that case,
他什么时候开始行动？
when will he deploy?
他说
He asked
让你来答复他何时行动。
that you decide when and send your reply.
如果是这样的话。
If so,
我们会在今晚午夜时分出发。
we set out tonight at midnight.
荒唐!
Absurd!
你不能在没有征求我意见的情况下这样做！"。
You can't do so without consulting me!
脇坂，请重新考虑。
Wakizaka, please reconsider.
从时间安排上考虑。
For procedure's sake.
我们必须在台风季节到来之前进行攻击。
We must attack
before the typhoon season arrives.
请原谅我的匆忙。
Pardon the haste.
你这个恶棍！
You scoundrel!
闭嘴！
Stop!
你的粗鲁将使你失去与我的结盟。
Your crude manner will cost you
my alliance.
你把战争看得太轻了，脇坂!
You take war too lightly, Wakizaka!
不要轻举妄动，
Don't be rash,
加藤。
Kato.
坐下来。
Sit down.
冷静下来。
Calm down.
加藤。放下你的剑。
Kato. Put down your sword.
我要一个答案。
I demand an answer.
告诉我。
Tell me.
你是否愿意与我联手？
Do you wish to join forces with me or not?
我们互相看不对眼。
Our dislike is mutual.
然而。
However,
大名命令我们一起发动进攻。
the lord chancellor ordered
our joint attack.
只要你收回你的剑，
Withdraw your sword,
我就当这次什么都没发生。
and I'll overlook this outburst.
加藤。
Kato.
加藤！
Kato!
你现在可以出来了。
You can come out now.
谢谢你。我听到了至关重要的信息。
Thank you. I heard crucial information.
我必须马上向全罗左道水军报告。
I must report back at once
to the Left Jeolla Navy.
我一直在盯着你。
I've been watching you.
所以那个女人让你溜进来了。
So that wench slipped you in.
了不起啊。
Remarkable.
连宫女们都来当间谍了。
Even the courtesans are spies.
真让人失望。
What a disappointment.
我希望能带你一起走。
I'd hoped to take you with me.
去死吧！
Die!
大人!
Dono!
退后！
Stand back!
快跑！
Run!
佐平！
Sahei!
抓住他！现在！
After him! Now!
你留在这里！
You stay here!
跟着我，真锅！
Follow me, Manabe!
他知道多少内幕？
How much does he know?
告诉我。
Tell me.
他在那里！在岸边！
There he is! By the shore!
- 快点。- 抓住他。
- Hurry.
- After him.
快上船。
Get in.
开火！
Fire!
火箭瞄准!
Aim the fire arrows!
射!
Release!
没有。
No.
除非你把你知道的一切都说出来。
Not until you spill everything you know.
大人，我们让你失望了。
Dono, We've failed you.
取走我们的命吧。
Please take our lives.
追捕所有的间谍。
Hunt down all the spies.
还有，
Also,
别杀她。
keep her alive.
求求你！我不是探子！
Please! I'm no spy!
我不是!
I'm not!
也许现在是时候
Perhaps now is the time
与过去决裂了，
to break with the past,
厘清所有的头绪。
tying up all loose ends.
求求你不要杀我!
Please don't kill me!
杀！
Strike!
[第三次海战，第一天]
DAY ONE, THIRD NAVAL CAMPAIGN
我们已经到达中途停靠的唐浦。向李水使报告。
We've reached Dangpo, our midway stopover.
Report to Admiral Yi.
遵命，大人。
Yes, sir.
我们是盟友！别打了！
We're allies! Stop!
把他也杀了！
Kill him, too!
脇坂!
Wakizaka!
告诉我。
Tell me.
谁在支持你？
Who is backing you?
是康兵卫吗？
Is it Kanbei?
鉴于我们之间的仇恨，
Given our mutual hatred,
你和我只有联合起来的时候才会起冲突。
you and I will only clash
if we join forces.
交出你们的船，然后滚蛋。
Surrender your ships and begone.
这样做，
Do so,
我会让你活下去。
and I'll let you live.
你以为偷了我的铁皮船就可以不受报应了？
You expect to steal my iron-plated ship
without retribution?
记住我的话。
Mark my words.
我一定会让你也尝尝这种侮辱的。
I will repay this insult.
现在我知道了。
Now I know.
从一开始你就计划好了。
From the start, you had this planned.
不过我无所谓把船都给你。
But my ships won't matter.
如果你想活命，就赶紧滚吧!
Begone if you care to live!
在大名的召唤下，
Summoned by the lord chancellor,
我已经回到了大阪城。
I've returned to Osaka Castle.
脇坂，你现在要摧毁朝鲜水师，
Wakizaka, you shall now demolish
the Joseon navy
并到达明朝的天津。
and reach Ming China's Tianjin.
征服那里!
Conquer the land!
一旦你成功了，
Once you do,
大名阁下将绕过朝鲜，
the lord chancellor will bypass Joseon,
直接前往明朝。
proceeding straight to Ming.
你将会是那一个
You shall be the one
在中国欢迎他到来的人。
to welcome him there.
金扇寄托了大名阁下的愿望。
The golden fan reflects
the lord chancellor's wishes.
请好好珍惜它。
Treasure it.
兄弟们，
Brothers,
我们将超过小西的第一师团和清正的第二师团
we will overtake Konishi's 1st
and Kiyomasa's 2nd divisions
作为第一个到达中国的人。
as the first to reach Ming China.
大人!
Dono!
我们向您表示祝贺!
We congratulate you!
划快点!
Row faster!
大人。李舜臣已经部署了他的舰队。
Dono. Yi deployed his fleet.
他的船只就在附近，已经到唐浦了。
His ships are nearby, already at Dangpo.
我明白了。
I see.
确实是一个强大的敌人。
A strong foe indeed.
在唐浦
Between Dangpo
和我们目前的基地云浦之间。
and our current base Ungpo.
看这里。
Look here.
我们之间的这条狭窄的海路，就是见乃梁海峡。
This narrow sea route between us,
Gyeonnaeryang Strait.
[见乃梁海峡]
GYEONNAERYANG STRAIT
你想起了什么地方吗？
Are you reminded of anywhere?
在龙仁之战中，
In the Battle of Yongin,
在前往汉阳的途中，有一条狭窄的小径。
there was a narrow pass
en route to Hanyang.
是在光教山吗？
In Gwanggyosan, was it not?
我们将驶向见乃梁，埋伏在那里。
We'll sail to Gyeonnaeryang,
lying in ambush.
我们将等待李舜臣的下一步行动。
We'll wait for Yi's next move.
- 现在就去。- 是的，大人！
- Now go.
- Yes, sir!
[唐浦，朝鲜水军中途停靠点]
DANGPO, JOSEON NAVY'S MIDWAY STOPOVER
我已经宣誓效忠于李水使。
I've sworn allegiance to Admiral Yi.
没有时间了。你现在必须独自前往。
There is no time. You must go alone now.
为了获得这份情报，许多人丢了性命。
Many lives were lost
to secure that report.
务必把它交给李水使。
Deliver it without fail to Admiral Yi.
快点！我们必须通过熊峙!
Hurry! We must pass Ungchi!
熊峙......通向全罗左道水军总部。
Ungchi... leads
to the Left Jeolla Navy Headquarters.
让后军加快速度！快没有时间了！
Hurry the rear guard! There is no time!
去全州要塞的捷径在这里...
The shortcut to Jeonju Fortress is
this way...
[唐浦，朝鲜水军中途停靠点]
DANGPO, JOSEON NAVY'S MIDWAY STOPOVER
我们已经检查了这些地区。
We've checked these areas.
现在我们在安骨浦和云浦附近搜索------。
Now we're searching
near Angolpo and Ungpo--
那你找到了隐藏的敌军舰队吗？
So, have you located
the hidden enemy fleet?
我们会的，很快。
We will, soon enough.
昨天刚刚抵达的情况下，我不愿意
I was loath to turn my back so soon
这么快就离开。
immediately upon arrival yesterday.
但如果今天还找不到敌人，
But if the enemy is not found today,
我将撤回我的人来协助保卫全州要塞。
I will withdraw my men
to help defend Jeonju Fortress.
我们今天会找到他们的。
We'll locate them today.
将军。我们已经找到了敌人。
Admiral. We've found the enemy.
- 在哪里？- 见乃梁海峡。
- Where?
- Gyeonnaeryang Strait.
见乃梁就在附近。
Gyeonnaeryang is nearby.
大约有100艘倭国舰船停靠在那里。
Around 100 Wae ships are docked there.
[唐浦见乃梁]
GYEONNAERYANG DANGPO
我们必须立即进攻。
We must attack at once.
命运是站在我们这边的。
Fortune is on our side.
他们停靠在见乃梁。
They're docked at Gyeonnaeryang
因为他们知道我们的舰队已经驶向了这些海岸。
because they know
our fleet has sailed out to these shores.
这改变不了什么。
That changes nothing.
我们必须谨慎行事。
We must be cautious.
移开其他桌子。
Remove the other tables.
- 遵命，大人。- 遵命，大人。
- Yes, sir.
我们必须把他们引到闲山的海上。
We must lure them here
to the open sea of Hansan.
见乃梁太窄了。
Gyeonnaeryang is too narrow.
我们的板屋舰不能在那里作战。
Our panokseon warships
cannot battle there.
我不同意。
I disagree.
无论窄不窄。
Narrow or not,
在敌人停靠的时候发动攻击会更容易。
it'll be easier to attack
while the enemy is docked.
我们以前的战斗队形难道不适合这种情况吗？
Wouldn't our previous battle formations
suit the circumstances?
海峡中的强大水流会阻碍我们船只的行动。
Strong currents in the strait will hinder
our ships' movement.
许多船会将被摧毁。
Many will be destroyed.
另外，攻击可能会无效，
Also, the attack may be ineffective
如果敌人逃到了岸上。
if the enemy flees to shore.
战争中的领导者不应回避
A leader in war should not shy away
微小的损失。
from small damages.
如果敌人逃到了岸上，
And if the enemy flees to shore,
他们只能跑到巨济岛上。
they can only run to Geojedo Island.
因为他们被切断了增援，
Since they'll be cut off
from reinforcement,
所以我们可以追击他们，在陆地上取得难得的胜利。
we can hunt them down
for a rare victory on land.
我说由我们来对他们进行攻击。
I say we strike at them.
在这种情况下，
In that case,
你为什么不带头发起第一次进攻？
why don't you take lead
with the first attack?
什么？
What?
你只想让我的战舰白白地受到攻击和损毁？
You want only my ships to get battered
and destroyed in vain?
我是要让你把敌人的船引到闲山这片开阔的海上。
I want you to lure the enemy ships
to this open sea of Hansan.
诱出舰队？
Lure out the fleet?
用鹤翼阵
To battle
进行战斗？
in crane wing formation?
这就是你所说的海上屏障吗？
Is that what you meant
by a barrier on the sea?
但我不是傻瓜。
But I'm no fool.
我不能用整个舰队仅有的七艘船去进攻。
I can't attack
with only seven ships in my fleet.
这是个自杀任务。
That's a suicide mission.
脇坂也不傻啊。
Wakizaka is no fool either.
你认为他会这么容易被引诱吗？
You think he'll be lured so easily?
我不会参与这个鲁莽的计划。
I'll take no part in this reckless plan.
将军您赢了!
Admiral Won!
敌人就在我们面前。
The enemy is right before us.
海上屏障？胡说八道!
A barrier on the sea? Nonsense!
算了，我还是去协助保卫全州要塞吧。
I'll help defend Jeonju Fortress instead.
作为一名水师向导，我可以引诱敌人。
As a hyangdo (naval guide),
I can lure the enemy.
我熟悉见乃梁附近的水路。
I know the waterways around Gyeonnaeryang.
让我去引诱敌人吧。
Let me lure the enemy.
我会代替你去的。
I shall go instead.
这个任务不应该落在老将身上。
The task should not fall
to the elderly commander.
这不合适。
It is not befitting.
求你了。派我去吧。
Please. Send me instead.
将军，我也这么认为。
Admiral, I agree.
[李英男队长] 请派我们去吧。
CAPTAIN LEE YEONG-NAM
Please send us instead.
你们两个家伙开始为李舜臣卖起命了！
I see you two are now serving Admiral Yi.
将军。
Admiral.
这是一位老将的最后愿望了。
It's the last wish of an old commander.
请批准吧。
Please grant it.
[鹤翼阵图]
CRANE WING FORMATION PLAN
海上的屏障？胡说八道!
A barrier on the sea? Nonsense!
你的作战计划是什么？
What is your battle plan?
鹤翼阵能确保胜利吗？
Will the crane wing formation
ensure victory?
[罗大用队长]
CHIEF NAH DAE-YONG
将军。宋军士报告。
Admiral. Sergeant Song reporting.
进来吧。
Come in.
什么风把你吹来了？
What brings you here?
一份绝密情报。
A report requiring secrecy.
这是由俊沙提供的。
It's from Junsa.
小早川的部队离开了锦山，开始进攻
Kobayakawa's troops left Geumsan to attack
全罗左道水军总部，而不是全州要塞。
the Left Jeolla Navy Headquarters,
not Jeonju Fortress.
敌人的水陆两军
The enemy's army and navy
会一起出击。
will strike in unison.
他们的舰队将于5日午夜开拔。
Their fleet was deployed
on the fifth at midnight.
如果他们的地面部队绕过全州要塞
If their ground troops bypass
Jeonju Fortress
来袭击我们的总部，
to strike our headquarters,
这将是一个致命的打击啊。
it will be a critical blow.
你向全州要塞发出警报了吗？
Have you alerted Jeonju Fortress?
俊沙正在去提醒他们的路上。
Junsa is on his way to alert them.
如果是这样。
If so,
谁替他送来了这份情报？
who delivered this report instead of him?
[熊峙径]
UNGCHI PASS
把大炮紧紧扣住!
Fasten the cannons tightly!
我不信任这些投降的倭兵。
I don't trust the anti-Wae fighter.
[抗倭士兵：已投降朝鲜的前倭军士兵]
ANTI-WAE FIGHTER:
FORMER WAE SOLDIER FIGHTING FOR JOSEON
敌人为什么要绕过全州要塞？
Why would the enemy bypass Jeonju Fortress
攻击水军总部？
to attack the navy headquarters?
我们丢下倭军降兵
Let's get rid of that anti-Wae fighter
按计划向全州行进吧。
and march to Jeonju as planned.
[义军统帅黄朴] 一旦敌人通过熊峙，
RIGHTEOUS MILITIA COMMANDER, HWANG BAK
Once the enemy passes Ungchi,
到水军总部只有半天的路程。
it's only a half-day's march
to the navy headquarters.
我们很快就会收到命令。
We'll receive orders soon.
在那之前，我们必须捍卫这个关口。
Until then, we must defend this pass.
你就是那个归顺的倭兵？
So you're the anti-Wae fighter?
跟着我。
Follow me.
如果我们能挺过这一关。
If we survive this,
我要请你豪饮一番。
I'll treat you to a hearty drink.
等等。
Wait.
没有这个必要。
No need for that.
共同的、正义的精神。这就是你需要的一切。
A shared, righteous spirit.
That's all you need.
还是穿点护甲吧。
Get some armor instead.
[鹤翼阵图]
CRANE WING FORMATION PLAN
我们将利用敌人的攻击来包围他们的舰队。
We will use the enemy's attack
to surround their fleet.
在闲山的海面上，我们将以鹤翼阵作战。
In the sea of Hansan,
we will battle in crane wing formation.
在旗舰的两侧，
Flanking the flagship
右翼中心由李亿祺将军坐镇。
on the right wing's center will be
Admiral Lee Eok-gi.
驻守左翼中心的是
On the left wing's center,
元将军。
there will be Admiral Won.
在他旁侧的是英明的鱼指挥，
By his side,
there'll be the wise Commander Eo,
他非常熟悉朝鲜的水路（水师向导）。
the hyangdo (naval guide)
well versed in Joseon's waterways.
而提供值得信赖建议的李云龙指挥，
Commander Lee Un-ryong,
who offers trustworthy counsel,
应该在他（元均）的另一侧。
shall be next to him.
金浣队长的操纵技术非常高超，
Captain Kim Wan,
who maneuvers with great skill,
将负责左翼先锋。
will be at the tip of the left wing.
指挥官权俊，
Commander Gwon Jun
拥有近距离格斗的速度和力量，
has the speed and strength
to wage close combat
会安排在右翼前锋。
at the tip of the right wing.
作为一名久经考验的并领导着我们水师最有力冲锋的战士，
As a proven warrior who leads
our navy's most forceful charges,
郑运指挥将会担当...
Commander Jung Un will be...
[致罗大用队长]
TO CHIEF NAH DAE-YONG
是不是所有船上的大炮都被命令装上双份弹药？
Were all ships ordered
to double-load their cannons?
是的，大人。
Yes, sir.
我们下达了装填双份炮弹和霰弹的命令。
We gave orders to double-load shells
and shrapnel shells.
为开战做准备。
Prepare for deployment.
遵命，大人。
Yes, sir.
所有的船都要参加战斗。
All ships to war.
所有船只!
All ships!
开战!
To war!
- 开战!- 开战！
- To war!
[第三次海战，第四天，闲山岛之战]
DAY FOUR, THIRD NAVAL CAMPAIGN
BATTLE OF HANSAN ISLAND
[见乃梁海峡]
GYEONNAERYANG STRAIT
大人!李舜臣已经部署了他的舰队。
Dono! Yi has deployed his fleet.
56艘战舰从唐浦起航。都是板屋船,
Fifty six ships set sail from Dangpo.
All panokseon warships,
没有看到龟船（盲船）。
no mekurabune (blind ship) to be seen.
这可能是一个圈套吗？
Could it be a deception?
不要介意龟船。
Never mind the mekurabune.
你们两个将在左右两翼进行埋伏。
You two will wait in ambush
on the right and left flanks.
- 遵命，大人！- 遵命，大人！
- Yes, sir!
我们必须诱敌出洞。
We must lure out the enemy.
与他们的船只保持至少200码的距离。
Stay at least 200 yards away
from their ships.
遵命，大人。
Yes, sir.
放下锚!
Lower the anchor!
[倭军左翼 真锅左马充]
LEFT FLANK
MANABE SAMANOSUKE
[倭军右侧 渡边七右卫门]
RIGHT FLANK
WATANABE SHICHIEMON
敌舰！前方发现敌舰！
Enemy ships! Enemy ships ahead!
不要开火! 先找到敌舰！
Hold fire! Find the enemy ships!
开火！
Fire!
第二队，准备开火！
Rank two, prepare to fire!
佐平。敌军有多少船？
Sahei. How many ships?
我们还看不清楚。
We cannot count yet.
守住位置。
Hold positions.
进行还击，牵住敌人。
Keep the enemy at bay by returning fire.
消耗他们的弹药。
Deplete their firepower.
- 遵命，大人！- 向右！开火！
- Yes, sir!
- To the right! Fire!
停火！
Hold fire!
向左！他们在左边！
To the left! They're on the left!
开火！
Fire!
左翼的真锅指挥官问他是否可以进攻。
Commander Manabe on the left flank
asks if he may attack.
右翼的渡边指挥官也在问。
Commander Watanabe on the right flank
asks the same.
告诉他们留在原地不要开火。
Tell them to stay in position
and hold fire.
他们必须埋伏等待。
They must wait in ambush.
遵命，大人！
Yes, sir!
指挥。我要倒转船头。
Commander. I will reverse the ship.
前进100码。
Advance 100 yards.
我们应该在这里停下。
We should stop here.
我们会被敌人包围的!
We'll be surrounded by the enemy!
照这样下去，敌人是不会上钩的。
At this rate, the enemy won't budge.
我们必须佯攻一下，才能引诱他们出来。
We must deliver a blow to lure them out.
向前划!
Row forward!
遵命，大人！
Yes, sir!
[见乃梁海峡外]
OUTSIDE GYEONNAERYANG STRAIT
敌人会上勾吗？
Will the enemy be lured?
所有船只待命。
Deploy the ships on standby.
遵命，大人。
Yes, sir.
指挥！雾气正在消散。
Commander! The fog is clearing.
我们的火药和炮弹已经不多了。我们必须撤退!
We're running low on gunpowder and shells.
We must retreat!
有大炮打来了！他们正在发射大炮！
Cannon fire! They're firing cannons!
他们在发射大炮？
Firing cannons?
开火！
Fire!
雾正在散去！我们可以看到那些船了！
The fog is clearing! We can see the ships!
只有三艘船。
Only three ships.
李舜臣怎么这么大胆。
How daring, Yi Sun-shin.
你很快就会后悔离开你的总部。
You shall soon regret
leaving your headquarters.
右侧发现倭舰!
Wae ships on the right!
这里有埋伏!
It's an ambush!
一次勇敢的尝试。
A brave move.
但三艘船还不足以引诱我们。
But three ships aren't enough to lure us.
我想知道，
How will Yi respond
一旦它们被击毁，
once they've burned down?
李舜臣将如何应对？
I wonder.
太晚了。
It's too late.
准备好近身战斗。
Prepare for close combat.
大人，左侧发现敌舰！
Dono, enemy ships on the left!
大人！是我们的船。
Sir! They're Joseon ships.
[李云龙指挥]
COMMANDER LEE UN-RYONG
全速行进！我们必须撤退！
Row at full speed! We must retreat!
划快点！我们必须撤退！
Row faster! We must retreat!
全速追赶他们。
Chase after them at full speed.
快点靠近!
Close in!
- 现在！- 是的，大人！
- Now!
- Yes, sir!
佐平！
Sahei!
立即给真锅打信号，让他停止追击。
Signal Manabe at once to stop his chase.
他绝不能离开见乃梁海峡。
He must not leave Gyeonnaeryang Strait.
遵命，大人！
Yes, sir!
大人，看那里！
Sir, over there!
是停止追击的命令!
Orders to stop!
我们该怎么做，大人？
What do we do, sir?
我们的剑已经出鞘了。
Our sword is drawn.
我们将在见乃梁这里抓住他们。
We'll catch them here in Gyeonnaeryang.
这是将军所希望的。继续追击他们!
It's what the general wants. After them!
他们的主力舰队并没有加入进攻。
Their main fleet isn't joining the attack.
向右舷转！
Rotate starboard!
扔抓斗！登船！
Throw the grapnel! Board the ship!
我们的船正在撞击礁石。
Our ships are hitting the rocks.
没关系，我们登上敌舰吧。
No matter,
we'll board enemy ships instead.
快点靠近!
Close in!
向左!转向左舷！
To port! Rotate to port!
啊！这怎么可能呢？
My word. How is this possible?
开火！
Fire!
真锅。
Manabe.
大人。
Dono.
将军!我们收到了来自见乃梁的报告。
Admiral! We received report
from Gyeonnaeryang.
李指挥的战舰已经驶入海峡了，
Commander Lee's ships entered the strait,
但是敌人的主力舰队还没有上勾。
but the enemy's main fleet
has yet to be lured.
所有前往见乃梁海峡入口的船只
All ships
to the mouth of Gyeonnaeryang Strait
变为箭矢阵型。
in arrowhead formation.
升起指挥旗。
Raise the command flag.
将军。
Admiral.
如果敌人从正面进攻，我们可能会有危险。
If the enemy attacks head-on,
we could be in danger.
水流对我们不利。
The current is against us.
我们需要他们来进攻。
We need them to attack.
升起旗帜。
Raise the flag.
遵命，大人。
Yes, sir.
升旗!
Raise the flag!
大人。
Dono.
敌人的主力舰队已经到了!
The enemy's main fleet has arrived!
所有船只，停止移动！
All ships, stop!
所有船只，停下！
现在，小早川应该已经穿过熊峙了。
By now,
Kobayakawa will have passed Ungchi.
开炮！
Fire the cannons!
我们需要更多的箭!
We need more arrows!
我们的山坡侧翼已经陷落了。
Our hillside flank has fallen.
我们寡不敌众啊!
We're far outnumbered!
退到第二防线！
Fall back to line two!
冲啊!
Charge!
第二道防线也无法守住。
Line two cannot hold.
我们必须退到第三道防线。
We must retreat to line three.
那将是我们和水军总部的末日。
That'll be the end for us
and the navy headquarters.
不!为了整个全罗道!
No! For all of Jeolla-do!
冲啊!
Charge!
敌舰！敌人正在前进！
Enemy ships! The enemy is advancing!
调转所有船只。增加划手。
Rotate all ships. Reinforce rowers.
所有划手都去划桨!
All rowers to oars!
增加更多划手!
Add rowers!
转动船身!
Rotate the ship!
准备开火!
Get ready to fire!
长官！那是指挥部的风筝。
Sir! It's the command kite.
我们必须加入编队!
We must join the formation!
再划快点!
Row harder!
[鹤翼]
CRANE WING
增加划手。全速前进!
Add rowers. Full speed ahead!
- 速度是对胜利的保证!- 是的，大人！
- Speed ensures victory!
- Yes, sir!
补充更多的船桨!
Add more oars!
划快点!
Row faster!
再快一点！
Faster!
用尽全力划!
Row with all your might!
再快一点！
Faster!
我们必须更快！
We must sail faster!
我要亲手毁掉你们，为真锅报仇。
I will avenge Manabe
by destroying you myself.
倭舰正在逼近!
Wae ships are closing in!
开火！
Fire!
射箭！
Shoot the arrows!
将军。他们在朝我们的船扔抓钩！
Admiral. They're grappling our ship!
切断绳索！
Cut the ropes!
我们必须恢复队形。
We must return to formation.
长官！鱼泳潭和李云龙指挥正在受到攻击。
Sir! Commanders Eo Young-dam
and Lee Un-ryong are under attack.
大人!
Sir!
掩护他!
Cover for him!
- 鱼指挥。- 跟着我！
- Commander Eo.
- Follow me!
鹤翼阵。不出所料。
Crane wing formation. As expected.
当我们用鱼鳞阵冲锋时，
Sahei can battle those ships
佐平可以与之一战。
while we charge in fish-scale formation.
变阵鱼鳞阵!
Fish-scale formation!
前线的渡边报告说
Watanabe reports from the front rank
他将向右翼落后的敌船发起冲锋。
that he will charge at the ships
lagging behind at the right wing.
他的想法和我一样。
He thinks just like me.
告诉他我允许了。
Tell him I permit the attack.
遵命，大人！
Yes, sir!
赶紧的!
Hurry!
向后划，装填大炮！
Row backward and load the cannons!
开火！
Fire!
他到底在想什么？
What in the world is he thinking?
他不顾波涛汹涌，毫无章法地开火。
He's firing without order
despite the waves.
他应该更清楚!
He should know better!
敌舰的速度太快了。
The enemy ships are too fast.
我们应该更早地进攻。
We should've attacked sooner.
你这该死的李舜臣，
You blasted Yi Sun-shin,
为什么还不开炮？
why aren't you firing?
元将军的舰队正在影响我们的阵型。
Admiral Won's ships are weakening
our formation.
请下达开火命令吧。
Please give order to fire.
请下达命令吧，大人！
Please give order, sir!
在开火之前，我们必须完成阵型部署。
Before firing,
we must complete the formation.
在倭国的三方原之战中，
In the Battle of Mikatagahara,
武田信玄摧毁了德川家的鹤翼阵，
Takeda Shingen destroyed
Tokugawa's crane wing formation
不是靠的刀枪。
not by swords or guns.
他用骑兵粉碎了对手。
He crushed it with cavalry.
向前冲，渡边。
Charge forth, Watanabe.
你和我将粉碎敌人
You and I will crush the foe
就像我们在光教山所做的那样!
as we did at Gwanggyosan!
向前冲锋。
Charge forth.
你们不是唯一有撞船的人。
You're not the only ones
with ramming ships.
看看我们安宅舰的威力吧（一种倭军大型舰艇）。
Behold the might of our antaekseon
(WAE large warship).
你的鹤在展翅之前就会坠下。
Your crane will fall
before spreading its wings.
我们现在逮住你了。
We've caught you now.
龟甲舰（盲船）。
Mekurabune (blind ship).
这是龟甲舰!
It's the mekurabune!
大人!
Dono!
把大号火铳拿来!
Bring the large gun!
现在!
Now!
这是龟甲舰!
It's the mekurabune!
更用力地划!
Row harder!
准备开火！
Prepare to fire!
更用力地划!
Row harder!
那艘旗舰被铁板挡住了。
That flagship is shielded by iron plates.
转向左舷，撞击船尾。
Rotate to port and ram its stern.
它很慢。
It's slow.
什么都没有，就是个瞎了眼的龟船。
Nothing but a blind mekurabune.
向李舜臣的旗舰进击！给舰队发信号！
Charge toward Yi's flagship!
Signal the fleet!
- 遵命，大人！- 遵命，大人！
- Yes, sir!
我们去船尾。
We'll go to the stern chaser.
我将亲自开炮。
I'll fire it myself.
侧面是它的弱点。
The sides were its weakness.
它一定会转过来。
It will rotate for sure.
我会瞄准侧面。
I'll aim for the side.
向龟船射击。
Take fire, mekurabune.
开火！
Fire!
右边的大炮，开火！
Right cannon, fire!
瞄准!
Aim!
开火！
Fire!
大人。
Dono,
龟甲舰正在向我军两侧射程外的地方靠近。
the mekurabune is closing in sideways
out of our firing range.
瞄准!
Aim!
佐平。
Sahei.
我信赖的堂兄弟。
My trusty cousin.
开火！
Fire!
等着瞧吧，李舜臣。
Wait and see, Yi Sun-shin.
你的龟船将成为你的牺牲品。
your mekurabune shall be your fall.
那艘船的船身较低，
That one has a lower hull,
更难瞄准。
harder to target.
龟甲舰向我们冲过来了!
The mekurabune is charging at us!
很好。
Good.
用尽你所有的力量冲向我们吧，龟甲舰。
Charge at us with all your might,
mekurabune.
一旦你这样做，你的头就会卡在我的船上。
Once you do,
your head will be lodged in my ship.
准备登船!
Prepare to board!
沐海潛（海怪）。
Bokkaisen (sea monster).
大人!
Dono!
将军。
Admiral.
新的龟甲舰拥有除撞击以外更多的用途。
The new turtle ship will achieve
more than ramming.
请。
Please.
请一定要让龟甲舰参加战斗！
Deploy the turtle ship.
李舜臣。
Yi Sun-shin.
这是你最后的伎俩吗？
Was this your final ploy?
将军。多亏了新的龟甲舰，
Admiral. Thanks to the new turtle ship,
鱼泳潭和李云龙指挥已经归队了。
Commanders Eo Hyang-do and Lee Un-ryong
have returned to formation.
将军。
Admiral.
敌舰就在附近。
The enemy ships are near.
我们必须开火了。
We must open fire.
将军!
Admiral!
为什么龟甲舰仍然在他们中间？
Why is the turtle ship still
in their midst?
龟甲舰向我们冲过来了!
The mekurabune is charging at us!
还有两百码的距离。我们可以追上它。
Two hundred yards away.
We can overtake them.
所有船只!
All ships!
分散阵形！
Break formation!
准备与敌军交战!
Engage the enemy!
瞄准!
Aim!
他到底在想什么？
What in the world is he thinking?
敌人就在我们面前。
The enemy is right before us.
我们不能再等了!
We can't wait any longer!
立即开火!
Fire immediately!
大人，我们没有炮弹了。
Sir, we're out of shells.
将军。
Admiral.
我们必须赢得这场战斗。
We must win this battle.
请开火吧。
Please fire.
一百码。
One hundred yards.
五十码。
Fifty yards.
把钩梯竖起来!
Raise the ladders!
所有船只。
All ships.
竖起钩梯!
Raise them!
转头。
Rotate.
转头!
Rotate!
左舷船桨，停下！
Port oars, stop!
右舷船桨，用力划!
Starboard oars, row harder!
太晚了，李舜臣。
Too late, Yi Sun-shin.
再用力一点!
Row harder!
登上他们的船！
Board their ships!
开火。
Fire.
海上屏障。
A barrier on the sea.
将军，你必须现在就开炮！
Admiral, you have to shoot now!
将军!
Admiral!
这是一个陷阱！
A trap!
开火！
Fire!
阻止他们！
Stop them!
我们决不能让他们通过!
We must not let them pass!
决一死战!
Fight to the death!
你到底是什么人？
What the hell are you?
我想请你喝一杯。
I wanted to treat you to a hearty drink.
太糟糕了，我不能。
It's too bad I can't.
快走!
Move!
你们这些入侵者别想
You invaders will not
越过熊峙。
go beyond this Ungchi Pass.
我们必须守住这个地方...
We must guard this place...
[义军指挥黄朴]冲啊！
RIGHTEOUS MILITIA COMMANDER, HWANG JIN
Charge!
我是怎么跟你说的？
What did I tell you?
这是一场正义之战。
It's a righteous battle.
一起战斗
Fought together
带着共同的信念。
with a shared spirit.
你们也是。
Yours as well.
对此我非常感激。
I'm thankful for it.
这场战争是什么？
What is this war?
一场正义与不义的战斗。
A battle of the righteous
against the unrighteous.
敌人逃跑了!
The enemy is fleeing!
追上他们!
Chase after them!
义
RIGHTEOUS
顺
FOLLOW
将军。这是一次彻底的胜利。
Admiral. It is a total triumph.
不。
No.
让我们继续努力吧。
Let us press on.
朝鲜所需要的
What Joseon needs
是一个决定性的胜利。
is a decisive victory.
[第三次海战，第六天，釜山附近的安骨浦]
DAY SIX, THIRD NAVAL CAMPAIGN
ANGOLPO, NEAR BUSAN
[第三次海战，第七天，釜山浦，决战之地]
DAY SEVEN, THIRD NAVAL CAMPAIGN
BUSANPO, FINAL BATTLEGROUND
[釜山浦，倭国水军总司令藤堂高虎]
WAE NAVAL COMMANDER IN CHIEF
AT BUSANPO, TODO TAKATORA
在1592年7月11日,
ON JULY 11, 1592,
李水使以对倭军的一次炮击结束了他在釜山浦的第三次海战。
ADMIRAL YI ENDED HIS THIRD NAVAL CAMPAIGN
WITH A CANNONADE ON THE ENEMY AT BUSANPO.
羽柴（丰臣）秀吉放弃了打败朝鲜水军的计划。
HASHIBA (TOYOTOMI) HIDEYOSHI QUIT
HIS PLANS TO DEFEAT JOSEON'S NAVY.
这阻击了倭军向西进犯大明，也扭转了战局。
THIS SAFEGUARDED MING TO THE WEST
AND REVERSED THE TIDE OF WAR.
你为什么带我到这里，大人？
What made you bring me here, sir?
[一年后，闲山岛]
A YEAR LATER, HANSANDO ISLAND
看看巨济岛。
Look at Geojedo Island.
这个岛正对着敌人的入海口。
The island is facing
the mouth of enemy waters.
我们必须加强对这片海域的控制。
We must secure tighter control
over this sea.
我同意，大人。
I agree, sir.
感谢我们之前在这片水域的胜利,
Thanks to our previous victory
in these waters,
釜山浦之敌
the enemy at Busanpo
尚未重新出现在闲山岛周围。
has yet to reappear
around Hansando Island.
我很欣赏这个名字。
I admire the name.
闲山。
Hansan.
的确，这是个有意义的名字。
Indeed, it's a meaningful name.
它代表着 "巍峨之山"。
It stands for "grand mountain,"
不是吗？
does it not?
确实如此。
It does.
这个面向闲山的见乃梁海峡
This Gyeonnaeryang Strait facing Hansan
将是我们的前线。
will be our front line.
愿闲山被证明是一座真正的巍峨之山
May Hansan prove to be
a truly grand mountain
守护我们的土地。
guarding our land.
这就是我的希望。
Such is my hope.
龟甲舰队已经抵达!
The turtle ships have arrived!
闲山：龙的出现
HANSAN: RISING DRAGON